PROFESSOR: So what kind of reasoning is
gonna go into adversarial search?
Well, we're gonna have an agent who's
trying to figure out what to do.
And just like in regular single-agent
search from before, the way we're
gonna decide what to do is we're
gonna think about the
consequences of our actions.
The difference is rather than thinking
about the sequence of actions that I
can perform, I need to think
about my opponent.
I imagine taking an action.
And then I imagine that my opponent
will then be in the situation of
thinking about what the
opponent should do.
And they're gonna imagine that
they're taking an action to
which I will respond.
And we'll get this embedded interleaving
of our future states.
So what's this gonna look
like in computation?
Well, remember back to the
single-agent case.
We drew these trees.
We callled them search trees.
And what a search tree had was at the
root it had the current position.
So here's the current state.
And here we have Pac-Man near a dot.
Well, in a single-agent tree
I can take an action.
And because I have two actions in this
case, left and right, I have two
possible futures.
And below that I have more futures.
And the search tree then goes
down until the game ends.
So, what happened in this tree?
Well, some of these paths go forever.
Some of these paths end because I've
eaten the last dot, and the game
terminates.
And what did we actually do?
Well, we imagine we associate
values with this.
So let's say this is the best possible
outcome where I go straight to the dot
and eat it.
And then there are various other
outcomes buried further
in the other trees.
And I can associate numbers with them.
So this is a search tree.
Current states are the root.
All possible futures then
branch out from there.
And what happened in the case of single
agent is I get to pick any
outcome I like.
I can pick any leaf in this tree.
In the actual search case, right,
we are minimizing costs.
And here we're gonna be talking
about maximizing values.
So if we really wanted to work out this
analogy, there would have to be
some sign changes.
I'm not gonna get into that.
For today, it's gonna be
maximizing values.
So the question is, what should we do?
Well, in a single-agent case it's
pretty clear what we should do.
We should find a way to make
this outcome happen, right.
And we can.
We just go right twice.
And no one's gonna stop us.
So we can essentially pick any leaf.
Let's formalize that.
Let's talk about taking this tree
and thinking about each
state having a value.
So what's a value?
A value is going to be a general idea
we're gonna use over and over again in
this course.
And the value of a state is the best
achievable outcome from that state.
And that's gonna be in terms of these
terminal utility functions.
So if I think about the root in this
single-agent case, I can look at this
and think, well, there are
a lot of outcomes.
Some of them are scored zero.
Some of them are scored eight.
But since I want the best and I can do
whatever I want, the value of the root
should be eight.
Well, let's go one more step
figuring that out.
Well, for terminal states
the value is known.
That's given, right.
In the definition of the game
I'm trying to solve, I know
the terminal values.
Just like in search I knew the costs.
What about the other ones?
So for example, what about
this state here?
Well, in this state here
I have a choice.
I can get the eight.
Or I can get whatever is down
below the left path.
So here, this state here
has some value.
Let's say it's six.
And if I have a choice between six and
eight and I'm maximizing, I should
take the eight.
So the value here should be eight.
And so in general, I can
write this equation.
I can write that the value of a state is
defined to be the maximum over its
children of the value
over the children.
So in some sense this is
stuff we already know.
The value of a state is the maximum
of the value of its children.
That's exactly how it works out
in the single-agent case.
OK.
Let's think about the case where
we have an adversary.
So here we have Pac-Man
trying to eat a dot.
And we also have a ghost.
If this is the root of the tree,
we can still do the same
thought process as before.
We can think, what are
the possible futures?
Well, I can still move left or right.
The difference is now in each of these
possible futures, the ghost can then
move left or right.
So there's still a tree
of possible futures.
From this left state, the ghost can
either come towards me and go camp the
dot, or it can go to the right.
OK.
And then over here, again,
the ghost has a choice.
So we have the exact same kind
of branching futures.
It's just like the single-agent case.
The only difference in this
tree is who controls what
happens at each node.
The actual tree itself is the exact same
kind of set of branching futures.
Everyone's in agreement about
what might happen.
But the two agents are in disagreement
about what they will choose to do.
And again, these trees in general go
on very deeply until the game ends.
And there gonna be various terminal
values at the bottom.
And I've illustrated a
couple numbers here.
So the question is now we still have
this tree, except we can't do we did
with a single-agent case and look at
this and say, oh, you know what?
I would like that plus eight or I would
like some number somewhere at
the bottom because our opponent
may not let us have it.
So we need to think about, now, what a
value is in the case of an adversary.
And this is gonna give us the
idea of a minimax value.
It's still gonna be the best outcome
we can achieve under perfect play
against an optimal adversary.
So it's still the best thing that we
can enforce, but now it has to
incorporate this idea of
adversarial reasoning.
So let's think about this.
We still know what's at the bottom
because the game defines
the terminal states.
So for all the terminal states at the
bottom of the tree-- and here I'm
imagining the tree is much smaller.
I imagine the game just ends after
this move and response.
So at the terminals we know the value.
We can look them up because
the game's over.
For a state that's under my opponents
control, I imagine that this ghost is
out here to minimize my value.
And so even though I may look out
and I may look and say that
plus eight's terrific.
I would love to have it, right.
It's just not gonna happen.
Because if we ever got to this state
that's highlighted here, what's the
ghost gonna do?
They're gonna go left.
They're gonna force the number
down to negative 10.
And so in essence here, this state's
minimax value is negative 10.
The computation here is fairly
straightforward.
I just figure out what the values of
the children are and I minimize.
That's what you do at a node
that the opponent controls.
Now a node that the agent controls,
we're gonna maximize.
So it's just like before.
So over here the opponent would have
forced us down to negative eight.
And then I look and I say, well, I'd
really love that plus eight.
But it's not an option, right.
I'm really only choosing between going
left to which I know the response will
be negative eight.
Or going right, which I know the
response will be negative 10.
And then that means over here, what I
should do is I should go left and I
should get negative eight.
So in other words, life is much,
much worse when there's
an adversary, right.
There's this nice plus eight, and the
ghost just won't let me have it.
Here's an example of a game tree that's
already pretty big for a game
that's pretty small.
So how many of you have
played tic-tac-toe?
How long did you play tic-tac-toe for?
Not very long.
Why do people stop playing
tic-tac-toe, right?
You learn the game tree pretty fast.
You know exactly what's gonna happen.
And what's gonna happen
in tic-tac-toe?
Second player is gonna force a draw,
unless one of the players is really,
really bad, like if they're
three years old.
OK.
But when adults play tic-tac-toe,
it's pretty boring.
So here's the tic-tac-toe game tree.
It's already pretty big even
though the game is simple.
It looks just like these
other game trees.
It alternates layers where the
maximizing agent here, the blue agent,
moves first, and then the minimizing
agent, and then the maximizing agent,
and so on until the game ends.
Now at the bottom, the utilities
are given here.
And they're a plus one for a win for the
max agent, minus one for a win for
the min agent, and zero for a draw.
We could do a bunch of computation
and figure out what the
value of the root is.
We probably all did this computation
at some point in our life.
So we kind of know what
the value is, right.
What is it?
We know the value at the root is zero.
But more importantly, even if you didn't
know that, you would know that
it's either plus one, minus
one, or zero, right.
It's not 0.7.
I guarantee you for any tree like this
that's got minus ones, plus ones, and
zeros at the bottom, no matter what
the value is at the root,
right, it's not 0.7.
Because the only operations we use
to compute the value at the root
are mins and maxes.
So you're gonna get at the root a
minimax value which is backed up by
some particular outcome, right, might
be that one, might be this one.
In practice, it's backed up by a bunch
of these for tic-tac-toe, right.
Because tic-tac-toe you
can force a draw.
That's an important point.
The minimax value isn't just some weird
aggregation of the whole tree.
It is some particular outcome or set of
outcomes which are minimax optimal
in the appropriate sense.
That means if you get a 4.3 at the root,
there's some leaf down there
that says 4.3.
So we've talked about what
this adversarial tree is.
And we basically already have an
algorithm for computing the
appropriate values.
That same algorithm that computes
the values will also tell us
the actions to take.
Because when we maximize, we'll want
to take the child or a child which
achieved the max.
So, for these kinds of deterministic
zero-sum games of perfect information,
we have a tree like this.
And it's very important to
conceptually break it up.
The terminal values are part of the
game, just like in search the cost of
the arcs were part of the
problem definition.
The algorithm you run propagates
things up the tree.
So we compute these recursively.
And we'll take the minimum of the
children at a min node, and we'll take
the maximum of the children
at a max node.
The number this returns at the root is
the minimax value of the root, as well
for the other nodes.
Let's think about how we
implement this thing.
And we basically already know because
we've done it by hand.
If we have a state and we're trying to
compute the value of this state under
the maximizing player,
well, what do we do?
We compute the values of
all of the children.
And then we take the maximum.
Let's think just for a minute exactly
how that works because this is gonna
get more complicated in a bit.
When we compute the maximum of a bunch
of children, the way we compute the
max is we start with this value
which is the max so far.
It's v here in the pseudocode.
The max so far starts out at negative
infinity as the edge case.
And then every time I see a child, I
improve the value of v if appropriate.
So if I see a child at seven,
now the max is seven.
If I see a child that's
10, now the max is 10.
So at all points, I've got this lower
bound which starts at negative
infinity and zips upward as
I examine the children.
And after I've seen all the children,
it's equal to the maximum.
So keep that in mind.
You start low.
And as you see the children, the
max so far slowly tics up.
Now of course to do this, I need
to be able to recurse.
And that means I need to be able
to compute the min value.
And so how do I do that?
Well, I initialize to
positive infinity.
And then as I compute all of the
children's values, I lower my value of
v. So when I compute a
min, I start high.
And it slowly tics low as
I examine children.
This'll be important later.
Now you notice that these
are mutually recursive.
And in fact, it's really pseudocode
because it's omitting
an important thing.
What's this omitting?
It's omitting the base case.
So if I just did this in a naive
way, it wouldn't work so well.
But we imagine that there's a case
the captures the terminal case.
And if it's a terminal, then you simply
return whatever the problem
tells you the terminal utility is.
This operationalizes the equations that
we had before, which is that at a
max node, the value of that node
is defined by the maximum
of the child values.
And at a min node, the value is
defined by the minimum of
the children values.
Now when you actually implement this,
you have to handle the base case.
And it's gonna turn out for your
projects you're gonna have to handle
other cases as well, nodes that
aren't pure min and max nodes.
And so a general way that's often
convenient to implement this is to say
no, no, no.
States simply have values.
How do I compute the value of a state?
If the state is a terminal state, then
I simply return it's utility.
Then I can have a dispatch.
And it says, if max controls this node,
then I'm gonna return the max
value of the state which will
do the appropriate thing.
If it's a min, then I'll do
the min value which will
do appropriate things.
And then I have these specific functions
just like before that always
call the dispatch.
And this is nice if you have multiple
mins in a row or, for next class, once
you have expectation layers.
So let's do an example.
And more importantly for this example,
since I know we can all do minimax
kind of by hand looking at the tree,
let's think about how this appears to
the recursive algorithm.
The tree doesn't just materialize and
you kind of see that plus eight in the
lower right corner.
Instead, it appears bit by bit
in a depth-first fashion.
So if I want to compute the minimax
value of this max node at the root,
well, I got to take a max
of a bunch of things.
So far the max is negative infinity.
So I look for the first child.
It's a min node.
So I need to know its value, which
of course involves recursing.
So I look at the first child.
The min so far is three.
The min so far is still three.
And there's no more children, so
I can stick a three right here.
Now at the root, the max has gone
up to three, but there are
more children to check.
So I check the second child.
I'm gonna take the minimum
of its children.
Its two.
It's still two.
So I write a two there,
and I can return that.
The max so far at the
root is still three.
Now I go to here, and I take the min.
So 14.
Now it's five.
Now it's two.
I return two.
And only now can the root say, all
right, the maximum is three, and it's
supported by this action, which is
in turn supported by this action.
So in fact, this is that magic node at
the leaf that's giving rise to the
whole minimax value at the root.
But the root minimax is three.
So now we have an algorithm.
How efficient is it?
Well, it's just like a
depth-first search.
You saw the procedure.
It recurses into each node.
It goes through the children from left
to right in whatever order they're
returned by the successor function.
That means the time and memory profile
are gonna be just like that
depth-first search.
The space isn't that bad because at
any time your storage is basically
what's on their recursion stack.
The time is bad news.
And why is it bad news?
The branching factor of the game is b,
which, for example, for chess is
something like 35.
The time is then b to the depth
that you have to search.
So how deep m can you go?
Well, in chess, how many moves
are there in a chess game?
Something like 100.
So for chess, the time complexity
is gonna be something
like 35 to the 100th.
That's not going to happen.
So the exact solution for something like
chess is completely infeasible.
Actually in this sense, I'm not even
sure we're gonna do it for checkers
anytime soon.
The methods that solve checkers
involved very aggressive
de-duplication so you didn't
have to look at the same
state in subtle variance.
So for the case of chess, the exact
solution is completely infeasable.
It's just not gonna happen.
But of course, we have chess
playing programs.
They do use minimax-like methods.
And so, somehow we need to be able to
actually play these games without
exploring the whole tree.
Let's think a little bit about the
properties this algorithm has.
So here's a little game.
Max controls the root.
Min controls the response.
Now let's think about what
the outcomes are.
Well, according to the minimax
algorithm, if we get to the left
branch, min has no choice
but to return 10.
On the right branch, what
will min return?
Nine.
And that means that at the
root, max can force a 10.
And that means max should
choose to go left.
Why?
Because even though that 100 is there
tempting you, you know min is not
gonna let you have it.
And so that right branch is only
worth nine in a minimax sense.
And this is exactly the correct
reasoning that you want if you're
playing against an evil mastermind.
So if you're playing against a perfect
player, this is exactly
what you should do.
You cannot achieve more than 10.
And if you do this other action and
you go to the right, you're gonna
achieve less.
You're gonna achieve nine.
Now that assumes a perfect player.
What if we don't have
a perfect player?
What if we have this guy?
Well, now the reasoning
isn't so clear cut.
The minimax value is still 10.
10 is the best you can achieve
against a perfect player.
Maybe against this guy you
have a shot at the 100.
So maybe you should go to the right.
Minimax does not include
this kind of reasoning.
We get to methods that will
in the next lecture.
Let's take a look about how minimax
reasoning can lead to suboptimal
behavior when you are not in fact
in an adversarial case.
Apologies for the grim nature we're
about to put Pac-Man in.
So, let's imagine these
are mastermind ghosts.
What's gonna happen?
It's not looking good for Pac-Man.
Now in this version of the game,
you get points when you win.
You get points when you eat a dot.
You lose a point every step.
So what should Pac-Man do?
He should dive-bomb the orange ghost
to stop a loss of points before the
inevitable failure.
So it's really, really grim.
And in fact, Pac-Man does
what you think.
The ghost do what you think.
Now, that is adversarial
worst-case reasoning.
What if these ghosts
aren't adversarial?
What if, in fact, they're
moving randomly?
I mean, look at them.
Look at those eyes, right.
These are not masterminds.
So if in fact they're moving
randomly, the orange guy's
coming towards Pac-Man.
There's not much we can do about that.
It actually doesn't have a choice.
The blue is either gonna
go up or down, 50-50.
If the blue one goes up,
it's gonna be bad.
If the blue one goes down,
we're actually gonna win.
And so rather than assuming the worst
case, we're basically in exactly the
tree I showed.
We're in the worst case, we should
just save that one point by
dive-bombing the ghost.
But, half the time we're
gonna do better.
And so let's see what Pac-Man
does in the average case.
Well, we lucked out.
And here we'll be able to get
through the whole game.
OK.
So we'll come back to that next
time, about how we can do
that kind of reasoning.
But for now we'll just realize
that against this guy,
you want to use minimax.
But if you are not playing against a
perfect player, if for example your
player is random, than minimax is
going to be overly pessimistic.
And we'll see the consequences
of that later.